Guide to the Harry J. Carman Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Harry J. Carman Papers,
1900-1964
Carman, Harry J. (Harry James), 1884-1964.
47 linear ft (633,000 items in 105 boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4078584
Biographical Note
Moore Professor of History, 1939-1964, and Dean of Columbia College, 1943-1950. Harry James Carman was a student at Syracuse and Columbia Universities, Principal of the Rhinebeck High School, Rhinebeck, N.Y., 1903-1913, taught history and political science at Syracuse University, 1914-1917, and was on the faculty of Columbia University for 46 years.
Scope and Content
Papers of Carman spanning his entire career beginning with his student days at Syracuse and Columbia Universities. His Columbia files include professional correspondence, lecture notes, course-related materia, and a bibliographical card index of American and European history. Dean Carman's abiding interest both in the academic and general communities is reflected in numerous special files which include correspondence to him as book review editor of HISTORICAL OUTLOOK, 1925-1929, as participant in Columbia's AMERICAN CULTURE SERIES, ca. 1935-1942, and STUDIES IN THE HISTORY OF AMERICAN AGRICULTURE, ca. 1935-1945. There are numerous files relating to his membership on the New York City Board of Higher Education, 1938-1964, the New York State Board of Mediation, 1941-1955, and the Japan American Committee on Intellectual Exchange. The many folders on American colleges attest to the Dean's concern for the quality and improvement of undergraduate education in the United States. Included are some of the working papers for PREPARATION FOR MEDICAL EDUCATION IN THE LIBERAL ARTS (published 1953), and THE RESURVEY OF PREPROFESSIONAL EDUCATION IN THE LIBERAL ARTS COLLEGE (published 1961). Among the few and incomplete book manuscripts there is a typescript of LINCOLN AND PATRONAGE (published 1943) with handwritten addition and correction.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 8 series:
Cataloged Correspondence
Series I: 1900 - 1945
Series II: 1940 - 1950
Series III: 1950-1956
Series IV: 1955-1959
Series V: 1955-1960
Series VI: 1959-1964
Series VII: Miscellaneous
Subjects
New York (N.Y.).--Board of Higher Education.; New York (State).--Board of Mediation and Arbitration.; Columbia College (New York, N.Y.)--Administration.; Columbia University--Students.; Columbia University--Faculty.; Syracuse University--Students.; Japan American Committee on Intellectual Exchange.; Rhinebeck High School (Rhinebeck, N.Y.).--Principal.; United States--History.; Europe--History.; Universities and colleges--United States.; Universities and colleges--New York (State)--New York.; Universities and colleges--New York (State)--Syracuse.; High schools--New York (State)--Rhinebeck.; Agriculture--United States--History.; History--Study and teaching.; Political science--Study and teaching.; Education--United States.; Bibliographies.; Lecture notes.; Scrapbooks.; Slides.; College teachers.; College administrators.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: 2-29. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1965 M-65 Carman, Margaret C. Gift
Gift of Mrs Margaret C. Carman, 1965.
- Cataloged Correspondence
  - Cousins, Norman To Carman, 1952-1954, (3 t.1.s.)
  - Eisenhower, D. W. To Carman, 1955, (1 t.1.s.)
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor To Carman, 1952-1953, (7 t.l.s., 1 t.l.)
- Series I: 1900 - 1945
  - Syracuse University, ca. 1900 - l914 (Box 1)
  - Syracuse University Continued (Box 2)
  - Early Financial Records, (ca. 1900 - 1920) (Box 2)
  - Rhinebeck High School, New York, (ca. 1910 - 1912) (Box 3)
  - Columbia University Student Days, 1914 - 1918 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Historical Outlook, l925 - 1929 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, (ca. 1928 - 1930) (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, A - C, (1930 - 1932) (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, D - Z, 1930 - 1932 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence Under Special Headings: Association of History Teachers Columbia University Press: Freeland: Heath and Company: Historical Outlook: League of Nations: Positions Wanted, 1930 - 1939 (Box 7)
  - Agriculture and Studies in the History of American Agriculture (1935 - 1945) Correspondence: (1935 - 1945) (Box 7)
  - Agriculture: Subject Files: A - Farm Labor Reports (Box 8)
  - Agriculture: Subject Files: Farm Population and Employment - W (Box 9)
  - Agriculture: 1) Correspondence: (1941) 2) Misc. Unsorted Materials (Box 10)
  - Agriculture: Misc. Unsorted Materials continued (Box 11)
  - Agriculture Scrapbooks (Box 12)
  - Misc. Correspondence, (ca. 1935 - 1940) (Box 13)
  - American Culture Series, (ca. l935 - 1942) (Box 13)
  - Columbia: Contemporary Civilization & Departmental Affairs, (ca. 1935 - 1945) (Box 13)
  - Misc. Files: Correspondence, Course Exams, etc., (ca. 1937) (Box 14)
  - Misc. Correspondence: 1) Unfinished Business: A - Z 2) Letters from Students, 1939 (Box 15)
- Series II: 1940 - 1950
  - A - B (Box 1)
  - C - Conference of Christians (Box 2)
  - Conference on 500 - E (misc.) (Box 3)
  - Ea - F (Box 4)
  - G..Hi (Box 5)
  - I - J (Box 6)
  - K - L (Box 7)
  - Labor Relations (Mediation): History of Labor Series, ., (ca. 1942) (Box 8)
  - Labor, J - N (Box 9)
  - Labor, P - W and New York State Board of Mediation/ Jules Freund (Box 10)
  - M (Box 11)
  - N.Y.C. Board of Higher Education, (l939 - 1943) (Box 12)
  - N.Y.C. Board of Higher Education General File, 1942 - 1952 (Box 12)
  - N.Y. C. Board Brooklyn College, l942 - 1952 (Box 13)
  - N. Y. C. Board City College Hunter College Queens College, 1942 - 1952 (Box 14)
  - N - Pr (Box 15)
  - Pr - S (general) (folder 3) (Box 16)
  - S (general) (folder 4) - Si (Box 17)
  - Sp - V (Box 18)
  - W - Z and Misc. Unsorted Material (Box 19)
  - Correspondence: (1944 - 1945) 1) Letters of Congratulations on Appointment as Dean of Columbia College 2) Letters of Condolence on Death of Mrs. Cathryne M. Barrett Carman (Box 20)
- Series III: 1950 - 1956
  - A - American Assembly (Box 1)
  - American Council on Education (1) (Box 2)
  - American Council on Education (2) (Box 3)
  - American Council on Education (3) (Box 4)
  - Ar - Bard College (l950 - 1952) (Box 5)
  - Bard College(l953 - 1955) - Board of Higher Education(l) (Box 6)
  - Board of Higher Education(2) - Colgate University (Box 7)
  - Columbia University - Coss (Box 8)
  - D - Earl Hall (Box 9)
  - Earlham College - Emigrée (Box 10)
  - F (Box 11)
  - Labor (Box 12)
  - Law - Ma (Box 13)
  - Mediation Board: Individual Cases, A - F (Box 14)
  - Mediation Board: Individual Cases, H - Z - National Concerts (Box 15)
  - National Conference Sub-Committee on Preprofessional Education of the Survey of Medical Education: Financial Records, 1952 (Box 16)
  - National Scholarship - Pa (Box 17)
  - Pe - Pres (Box 18)
  - Pu - S (general) (Box 19)
  - Sa - Sy (Box 20)
  - T - Whitney Foundation, 1950 - 1951 (Box 21)
  - Whitney Foundation (l952-1955) - Z and Misc. Unsorted Material (Box 22)
  - Japan Committee on Intellectual Exchange Committee(ca.1950-1960) General Files: 1) Folders 1 - 12 2)A - Ca (Box 23)
  - Japan Committee: 1) General Files: Co - P: 2) Visitors to Japan: American Personal Name File (Box 24)
  - Japan Committee: Correspondence: Japanese Personal Name File, A - Ta (Box 25)
  - Japan Committee: 1) Correspondence: Japanese...Name File, Ta - S 2) Account Books 3) Printed Matter (Box 26)
- Series IV: 1955-1959
  - A - C (Box 1)
  - D - Mac (Box 2)
  - Man - R (Box 3)
  - The Resurvey of Preprofessional Education in the Liberal Arts College Conference on the Resurvey... (1958): 1) Correspondence 2) Working Papers (l) (Box 4)
  - The Resurvey ...: 1) Working Papers(2) 2) Colleges Visted by Dean Carman (A - Z) 3) Pre-medical Material 4) Miscellaneous Material (Box 5)
  - S - Z and Misc. Unsorted Material (Box 6)
  - Ethics (Institute of Ethics for the Institute for Religious and Social Studies of the Jewish Theological Seminary) (Box 7)
- Series V: 1955-1960
  - A - K (Box 1)
  - M - Z and Misc. Unsorted Material: (1956-1958 [1]) (Box 2)
  - Misc. Unsorted Material, l958[2] - 1960 (Box 3)
- Series VI: 1959 - 1964
  - A - B (Box 1)
  - C (Box 2)
  - D - G (Box 3)
  - H - N (Box 4)
  - O - T. (Box 5)
  - 1) U - Z and Misc. Unsorted Material, 1961 - 1964 (Box 6)
  - 2) Correspondence re: Carman's 75th birthday, 1959 (Box 6)
- Series VII: Miscellaneous
  - Lincoln and Patronage, ( manuscript and typescript with ms. corrections) (Box 1)
  - Lincoln and Patronage, ( Typescript (without t. - p.)) (Box 1)
    [On Patronage in N.Y. State]
  - Mss.: Misc manuscripts and typescripts, including some speeches (Box 2)
  - Mss.: Misc. typescripts submitted to Carman (1) (Box 3)
  - Mss.: Misc. typescripts submitted to Carman (2) (Box 4)
  - Mss.: Misc. typescripts submitted to Carman (3) (Box 5)
  - Lecture Notes (includes: clippings; reprints; course-related material): American History (l) (Box 6)
  - Lecture Notes: American History (2) (Box 7)
  - Lecture Notes: American History (3) (Box 8)
  - Lecture Notes: American History(4) (Box 9)
  - Lecture Notes: Economics (Box 10)
  - Lecture Notes: European History(l) (Europe: 1500 - 1800) (Box 11)
  - Lecture Notes: History 15 - 16 (Box 12)
  - Lecture Notes: European History (2) (Europe: 1800 - 1921) (Box 12)
  - Lecture Notes: European History(3): *1) History 20; 2) Geographical File(1): A - Germany (Box 13)
  - Lecture Notes: European History(4): 1) Geographical File; 2) Gt. Brit. - Scand (Box 14)
  - Lecture Notes: World History: 1) Asia; 2) Africa (Box 14)
  - Lecture Notes: Government and Politics (l) (Box 15)
  - Lecture Notes: Government and Politics (2) (Box 16)
  - Lecture Notes: History of Science (l) (Box 17)
  - Lecture Notes: History of Science (2) (Box 18)
  - Lecture Notes: Miscellaneous Files (Box 19)
  - Columbia University Course - Related Material: Course Syllabi (Box 20)
  - Columbia University History Exams (Box 21)
  - Columbia University History 90 Exams (Box 22)
  - Columbia University 1) History 182 (Box 23)
  - Columbia University 2) History 187 (Box 23)
  - Columbia University 3) Misc Notes (Box 20)
  - Card Files: 1) Contemporary Civilization A1 - A2: Lecture Notes 2) Bibliography: A - Z (Box 24)
  - Card Files: American History Bibliography (1) (Box 25)
  - Card Files: 1) American History Bibliography (2) 2) European History Bibliography 3) Memorabilia (Box 26)
  - Miscellaneous: 1) Personal Documents 2) Inscribed Reprints 3) WMCA Radio Editorials: ca. l958-1959 4) Misc. Notes and Bibliographies (Box 27)
  - Miscellaneous: 1) Columbia role books 2) Memorabilia (Box 28)
  - Black and white glass slides depicting environment and life of farm laborers (i.e., share croppers, tenant farmers, and migrant laborers) during the 1930 depression years. (Box 29)